Raushan Kumar Jha

Email: jha.rau@northeastern.edu Mobile: 8577015680 Linked In

An enthusiast Java Developer having experience of 2 years in Web Application Development. Experienced in all phases of the Software Development life cycle from business requirement analysis, development, testing the system till implementing the changes in production and maintenance support.

EDUCATION

Northeastern University

Boston, MA

Master of Science in Information Systems

Sept 2022 - Present

Vellore Institute of Technology

Vellore, India

Bachelor of Technology in Electronics and Communication Engineering; GPA: (9.56/10.0)

July 2016 - June 2020

Programming Skills

- Languages: Java, SQL, Javascript
- Technologies: HTML5, CSS3, React.js, Node.js, jQuery, JSON, XML, RESTAPI.
- Software Tools: Git. Bitbucket, Jenkins, Bash, Postman, Eclipse, Visual Studio, Control-m, My SQL, Jira

EXPERIENCE

Tata Consultancy Services

Bangalore, India

Application Developer Aug 2020 - Aug 2022

- o Development life cycle: Walked in through all phases of the Software Development life cycle for Insurance and Annuity systems from business requirement analysis, development, testing the system till implementing changes in production and maintenance support. Involved in the code reviews, Design discussions, development and deployments in all regions.
- Change requests delivery for enhancement: Delivered more than 50 change requests without post-production defects within committed deadlines.
- REST based microservices: Implemented REST based microservices to provide Agent related data to various business departments.
- o Databases: Hands-on expertise in databases. Worked on many changes which needed to be done for any new column or existing column in database.
- Bugs: Worked on code debugging and troubleshooting the bugs. Solved critical bugs in database query execution leading to a 80 percent reduction in server-side crashes and successful responses.
- Scheduler creation: Created Schedulers which run on regular basis i.e, weekly or daily and coded for the target.
- Agile method: Familiar with Agile development methods. Helped business users in getting their requirements for change requests complete. Co-ordinating with QA team to carry out testing on the changes. Aligned with Change Release Management.
- o Jenkins and Azure deployments: Worked and collaborated with the DevOps team by building Jenkins pipelines for deployments from Dev to Prod regions, and Azure deployments.
- Major Incidents: Involved in the Major incident calls and worked on documenting application descriptions and root cause analysis for major incidents. Fully SLA compliant by responding and resolving incidents assigned on

Axxela Advisory Services LLP

Kolkata, India

Analyst- Internship

Jan 2020 - Jun 2020

- Requirements analysis: Worked on various requirements and made reports and dashboards which give insights to clients and the company in decision making.
- Reports: Developed exhaustive reports outlining the company's current performance, goals, resources, and performance gaps.

Projects

- Fuel Theft Alarming System: Developed digital Indicators to eradicate fuel theft so that it can help us know the exact quantity of fuel available before refuelling and after the refuelling is done.
- Bluetooth Controlled Bot: Developed Bluetooth wireless technology to control our robot, and used mobile phone as a remote control which has built in Bluetooth feature.
- Rainwater detector: Developed detector which helps in detecting the rain and alert the user. The rain status is displayed so that one can make some actions for rain water harvesting and automate the water harvesting processes.